Hi there. My name is Holt Skinner and
I'm a developer advocate for Google
Cloud AI.
Google Cloud just announced Gemini
Enterprise Agent Platform, which
includes everything developers need for
creating enterprise grade, scalable, and
secure agents.
So, let's break down all the key parts
and how they fit into the development
life cycle for AI agents.
Agent Platform's features are focused
around four key parts of the agent
development life cycle: build, scale,
govern, and optimize.
Everything that is mentioned in this
video has tutorials and documentation in
the GitHub repository, also linked in
the description.
So, be sure to check them out afterwards
and try everything out for yourself.
Before we start, a quick note on the
name. If you've been building with
Vertex AI, you're in the right place.
Agent Platform is an evolution of Vertex
AI, including Model Garden and Model
Training, that is now restructured as an
agent-first ecosystem. So, you'll see
some mixed terminology as we transition,
but please be assured that the core
Vertex AI functionality remains
unchanged. And special thanks to Eric
Seeta, Natasha, Karen, Allison, and the
entire Cloud AI DevRel team for their
assistance in preparing this video.
First, if we want to build an agent, we,
either a human or an agent, need to
write some code.
Google uses Agent Development Kit, or
ADK, as the framework to build agents.
It currently supports four languages:
Python, TypeScript, Java, and Go.
ADK is a comprehensive framework for
building various types of agents,
ranging from simple sequential agents to
complex multi-agent systems. And in the
latest version, you can build
deterministic graph-based agents. So,
you can choose between fully dynamic,
model-led reasoning, or more strict
deterministic logic.
While optimized for Gemini, ADK provides
integration with any model, including
Cloud and Anthropic or open weight
models from Ollama.
This flexibility lets you mix and match
models to meet the needs of your agent
tasks, whether strictly text-based or
using a mix of multimodal data.
When you're designing your agent, you'll
want to connect to external tools. The
standard pattern is to use Model Context
Protocol, MCP, which is fully supported
by ADK.
And if you want to connect to external
agents, ADK has built-in support for
agent-to-agent protocol.
You can collaborate with any agent, no
matter what framework it was created in
or where it's running.
Multi-agent systems can be built like
microservices, and A2A describes the API
surface. So, every remote agent supports
the same data structures and methods.
Most agent frameworks, like LangGraph,
CreAI, and AG2, have built-in support
for A2A.
To get started with ADK, you can fire up
your favorite IDE, then head over to
adk.dev, select your language of choice,
choose your design patterns, select a
model from Model Garden, and get
running.
ADK provides a batteries-included
toolbox for architecting agents. But
what about agentic assisted development,
or vibe coding? This is where Agent CLI
shines. It is a full programmatic
interface for coding agents, which can
automate the core tasks of creating and
managing ADK agents. Specifically, it
offers Agent Skills for AI assisted
development, automated evaluation to
quickly measure agent efficacy, and
automated deployment to agent runtimes
and the Gemini Enterprise app.
And if you want a low-code visual
builder for building agents, then you
can use Agent Studio in the Cloud
Console. It lets you map out your agent
flows, test them in real time, and see
exactly how the model reasons through a
conversation.
Once you're happy with the flow, you can
deploy it directly to Agent Runtime or
export the logic as ADK code, which can
then be deployed to Cloud Run, GKE, or
anywhere you like.
You can mix and blend your development
workflow, operating between Agent CLI
and Agent Studio, or just write code
from scratch the old-fashioned way.
If you don't want to start with a blank
IDE, you can find lots of pre-built
agents in Agent Garden to give you a
head start. It's a library of
high-quality templates for common
enterprise patterns, like financial
analysis or marketing campaigns, that
you can then deploy and customize as
needed.
Okay, let's say you made a great agent.
It works on your machine. Now, how do
you deploy it and get it running in
production?
Well, you can deploy and serve your
agent on Agent Runtime. Agent Runtime is
a managed platform as a service
specifically designed for the needs of
enterprise-ready agents.
For example, it includes less than
1-second cold starts and supports
long-running agents that can keep
reasoning for up to 7 days.
While it's optimized for ADK, Agent
Runtime is framework agnostic. So, you
have the flexibility to deploy agents
built in LangGraph, LangChain, or your
own custom stack.
Now, when an agent is running in a
shared environment, it's common to have
multiple users, which will each have
multiple conversations with the agent.
So, how do you manage these?
Agent Sessions keeps track of
interactions between a user and agents.
If you're using ADK on Agent Runtime,
these are stored and handled
automatically. You can also create
custom session IDs, which lets you map
interactions directly to your internal
customer records or project IDs.
When a user has a lot of interactions
with an agent, it's really important for
the agent to remember things over time,
so the user doesn't need to provide this
every time.
You can add this capability to your
agent using Memory Bank.
If you need your agent to execute code
or interact with a UI in some way, like
a legacy application that doesn't have
an API, then you can use Agent Sandbox
to have a safe environment for the agent
to do whatever it needs to do.
Okay, we're deployed. So, that means
we're ready to go in production, right?
Well, not exactly. We need to talk about
agent governance. So, why does this
matter? It gives you the safety and
control needed to actually trust your
autonomous agents with real business
tasks, instead of having to constantly
baby sit them.
When you have autonomous agents acting
on behalf of users, we have several
problems. How do we know which agent is
taking a specific action? Agent Identity
answers that question. When you deploy
an agent to Agent Runtime, every agent
gets its own IAM principle.
Another problem is how to keep track of
all the agents spread across Google
Cloud. Agent Registry handles this by
automatically cataloging agents deployed
to Agent Runtime, GKE, Gemini
Enterprise, and Google Workspace. It
also automatically catalogs first-party
MCP servers and MCP servers from Apigee.
Additionally, you can register
third-party A2A agents and MCP servers,
which lets your agents in Google Cloud
access them securely.
The next logical problem to solve is
access management. Which agents have
access to specific tools and other
agents? You can set IAM policies on
agents, tools, and the registry itself
through Agent Policies.
Model Armor templates can be defined
along with Sensitive Data Protection to
sanitize both input prompts and
responses from an agent, which blocks
prompt injections and PII leaks.
To efficiently scale and enforce these
policies, Agent Gateway acts as a single
entry point. It intercepts all ingress
and egress calls to audit or enforce the
policies. And because agents aren't
always 100% predictable, anomaly
detection uses an LLM as a judge
framework to watch reasoning patterns
and flag behavior that looks weird or
stalled. You can see all agent-specific
threats in the curated Agent Security
dashboard.
When you're running an agent in
production, the quality of responses and
actions taken is incredibly important.
However, agents are highly complex
systems with non-deterministic behavior,
so it can be really difficult to
troubleshoot when something goes wrong.
This is what Agent Observability is used
for, giving full visibility into agent
decision-making. You get turnkey
dashboards and automatic tracing to see
exactly why an agent made a decision,
what tools it called, and where the
logic went sideways.
And when you have multi-agent systems or
lots of MCP servers, it can be
challenging to visualize what all is
included in the system. So, you can use
Agent Topology to get a graph-like view
of all the agents and MCP servers in a
system and view aggregated traces for
them.
In regular software development, you'll
typically write unit or integration
tests to verify that the behavior stays
consistent when you make a code change.
But unlike traditional software,
generative AI is inherently
non-deterministic, which makes testing
crucial but highly complex. So, this is
how you can use Agent Evaluation. You
can automatically evaluate even complex
multi-step interactions.
Taking this a step further, we know that
there are infinitely more edge cases to
consider when building an AI agent
versus deterministic systems. But it's
impractical to manually write test cases
for all these possibilities. So, you can
use Agent Simulation to automatically
generate thousands of sample
interactions to test with, ideally
before you push to prod.
Because we're running at high scale, it
can make sense to automate making
improvements to our agent over time when
failures occur. This is how you use
Agent Optimizer. It refines your
instructions based on failure signals,
creating continuous feedback loop
designed to improve your agents.
Building enterprise grade agents doesn't
have to mean duct taping a dozen
different tools together. Agent Platform
is designed to give you a clean path
from your first lines of code to running
securely in production. Check out the
links in the description for official
documentation, the GitHub repository,
and tutorials to try out for yourself.
We can't wait to see what you build.